

■ i@disksing.com | ♣ https://disksing.com | • disksing

### **Summary**

I am a developer with more than 10 years of experience, currently focusing on **distributed systems**. I am looking for work in the direction of **distributed databases**, **storage systems**, and **scheduling systems**.

I have rich experience in Go and C++ development, and I am expert in design and architecture of **highly available** distributed systems. I would prefer a technologist type job to a management oriented position.

## Work Experience \_

PingCAP, Inc. ☐ Beijing, China

DATABASE DEVELOPER

Oct. 2015 - Present

- Designed and implemented **distributed transaction** of *TiDB* 2. Fully support ACID features in distributed environment. Correctness and performance are verified by more than 1000 production clusters.
- Designed and implemented a distributed scheduling system for multi-raft storage systems to meet high availability and cluster disaster recovery capabilities, and also provide cluster load balancing.
- Leading the design of the **cross data center deployment** architecture of TiDB, including various deployment schemes such as Three Data Centers, Three Data Centers in Two Cities and Two Data Centers in One City.
- Designed and implemented a replica placement system @ for multiple deployment scenarios and HTAP architecture.
- Leading the design of a **distributed timestamp allocation scheme** 🗗 across data centers while guarantees strong transaction consistency.

Sincetimes, Inc. ☐ Beijing, China

GAME DEVELOPER & TECH LEADER

May. 2012 - Sep. 2014

Responsible for the development of several web games and mobile game servers. Made several extensive changes to the company's server
framework to accommodate new game genres.

Changyou, Inc. ☐Beijing, ChinaGAME DEVELOPERMar. 2010 - May. 2012

• Participated in the development of a 2D MMORPG game.

#### **Education**

#### **DLUT(Dalian University of Technology)**

Dalian, China

B.S. IN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING Sep. 2006 - Jul. 2010

#### **Publication**

2020 **VLDB 2020**, *TiDB: A Raft-based HTAP Database* ♂

#### Honors

Bronze Medal, TiDB Hackathon 2019, Embracing Elasticsearch: Giving TiDB the wings of full-text search ☑ Bronze Medal, TiDB Hackathon 2018, TiQuery: All Diagnosis in SQL ☑

## **Projects**

- TiDB (PingCAP): open source distributed HTAP database compatible with the MySQL protocol ♂
- $\bullet \ \ \textbf{TiKV (PingCAP)} : \textit{Distributed transactional key-value database, originally created to complement TiDB \ \ \textbf{Z} \\$
- PD (PingCAP): Placement driver for TiKV ♂
- iter (Side Project): Go implementation of C++ STL iterators and algorithms ♂
- Luson (Side Project): Self-hosted JSON API server ☑

# Articles (in Chinese).

- Understanding external consistency ☐
- TrueTime and atomic clock ♂
- From learning Paxos to understanding Raft ♂
- Evaluating failure probability ♂
- Understanding multi replica of TiKV ♂
- Even node Raft can be useful ♂
- Understanding F1 online schema change ♂

August 2, 2021 Huang Menglong · Résumé